<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pack of old Puritans· maintaining the unlawfulness &amp; inexpediency of subscribing the new engagement. Professing the dissatisfaction of their judgements, and the unresolvedness of their consciences, with Mr. Jghn [sic] Dury's Considerations and just reproposals concerning it. And answering the most material allegations that are urged by him or others for subscription.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90499</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863177</idno>
  <idno type="VID">165546</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240915751</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E593_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863177</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863177e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90499)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165546)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 91:E593[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pack of old Puritans· maintaining the unlawfulness &amp; inexpediency of subscribing the new engagement. Professing the dissatisfaction of their judgements, and the unresolvedness of their consciences, with Mr. Jghn [sic] Dury's Considerations and just reproposals concerning it. And answering the most material allegations that are urged by him or others for subscription.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Company of Covenant-Keepers, dwelling in Great Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "Just re-proposals to humble proposals" and "Considerations concerning the present engagement, whether it may lawfully be entered into, yea or no?", both by John Dury.</note>
                  <note>In this edition line 11 of title page ends: just.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 22 1649"; the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Dury, John, 1596-1680. --  Just re-proposals to humble proposals.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Dury, John, 1596-1680. --  Considerations concerning the present engagement, whether it may lawfully be entered into, yea or no?</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165546:1"/>
            <p>A PACK <hi>OF OLD</hi> PURITANS.</p>
            <p>MAINTAINING THE Unlawfulness &amp; inexpediency</p>
            <p>Of subscribing the new ENGAGEMENT.</p>
            <p>PROFESSING The dissatisfaction of their judgements, and the unresolvedness of their Consciences, with Mr. JOHN DURY'S Considerations and just Reproposals concerning it.</p>
            <p>And answering the most material Allegations that are urged by him or others for subscription.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MAT. 18. 26.</bibl> In the mouth of two or three Witnesses, every word shall be established.</q>
            <p>LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by the Company of Covenant-Keepers, dwelling in Great</hi> BRITTAIN. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:165546:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>John Duries</hi> just Reproposals, page 1. line 6.</bibl>
               <hi>IT is neither just nor conscionable, that any matter should be pressed upon the Conscience of any, as a duty, otherwise then by clear demonstration of the righteousness thereof, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of the judgement therein.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>Cayroll</hi> in his Sermon (worthy of serious considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Covenant-breakers of these times) preached <hi>October</hi> 6. 1643. at the Assembly for taking the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</bibl>
               <hi>WHere Conscience is indeed unsatisfied, we should ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pitty, then impose; and labour to perswade, rather then violently to obtrude,</hi> page 16.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>Iohn Goodwins</hi> Anti-cavelarisme.</bibl>
               <hi>HE that refuseth to obey a Superiour an unlawfull Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, giveth notice to him, that his foot is in a snare of death, and that his preservation stands in his desisting and Repentance.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165546:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE</hi> CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>AS there is no <hi>Poast</hi> so rotten, but through the <hi>Painters</hi> Art and Industry, may easily be cast into the <hi>forme</hi> and <hi>colour</hi> of a <hi>marble Piller:</hi> So (Christian Reader) there is no <hi>action</hi> so cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and (rotten in it self) but if it may be of use to <hi>support a prevailling faction,</hi> shall have many who will straine both their braines and Consciences to cast it into such a colour as may render it most <hi>subservient</hi> to that <hi>designe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the proof of this, we shall need to produce no other <hi>Evidences,</hi> and <hi>Instances,</hi> then those new <hi>State Chaplains,</hi> who daily appear like so many <hi>parascitical Painters</hi> in their severall Pamphlets, to <hi>varnish over</hi> that <hi>complicated piety</hi> of subscribing the <hi>new Engagement,</hi> with the <hi>orient colours</hi> of an <hi>indispensible duty, necessary, just and equall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although to teach others to break the <hi>least of Christs Commandements,</hi> will certainly hinder the spiritual and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal advancement of all such <hi>Doctors of disobedience;</hi> for <hi>Christ</hi> who is the <hi>truth it self,</hi> hath said, <hi>That he which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth others to break the least of his Commandements, shall be called the least in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Mat. 5. 26.</p>
            <p>Yet have the aforesaid <hi>Tutors</hi> shewed too much of the old <hi>Serpents subtilty,</hi> in teaching the <hi>black Art</hi> of breaking,
<pb facs="tcp:165546:3"/> all sacred bonds and obligations whatsoever, and that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of <hi>satisfying</hi> the <hi>Consciences,</hi> and <hi>resolving</hi> the scruples of such who cannot swallow down this cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel of perjury as easily as themselves.</p>
            <p>That we might therefore be satisfied in our judgement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and resolved in our Consciences, about this great businesse of <hi>subscribing</hi> the ENGAGEMENT. We have seriously vowed and weighed what hath been written by Mr. <hi>DURY.</hi> By the <hi>Northern Subscribers in the Plea.</hi> In the ENGAGEMENT <hi>vindicated.</hi> In the <hi>Logical Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of the lawfulness of subscribing the new</hi> ENGAGE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT. And in the <hi>Explanation of the Covenant, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the taking the</hi> ENGAGEMENT, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But finding all these <hi>Pamphlets</hi> to be full of <hi>irreligious</hi> and <hi>irrational Arguments,</hi> and not in the least <hi>satisfying</hi> to any, except such who are willing to <hi>couzen</hi> their <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> we hold it our duty, the Lord <hi>having lighted our Candle,</hi> not <hi>to put it under a bushel.</hi> But <hi>publish</hi> the grounds of our <hi>dissatisfaction with them all.</hi> And especially with Mr. <hi>JOHN DURIES Considerations and just Reproposals,</hi> which (although, through their often printing or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression</hi>) we fear hath taken too much impression <hi>upon weak and unstable soules:</hi> yet have we found them so full of contradictions, absurdities, and irrationall reasonings, vented with such heights of Majesterial confidence, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, as makes us fear, that if ever he had any <hi>ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial gifts or abilities,</hi> they are, by the just judgement of God, <hi>blasted,</hi> for undertaking a service so <hi>sinfull,</hi> as to render him <hi>accessary</hi> to the <hi>perjury</hi> of all those persons who have subscribed the new ENGAGEMENT by his <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:165546:3"/>
            <p>Although therefore the <hi>Reverend, Learned,</hi> and <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Authour of the Proposals,</hi> nor any other of his own <hi>Function</hi> (as we conceive by their silence) will not so farre undervalew themselves, or disparage their judgements by vouchsafing an Answer to his weak and worthlesse Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, because he hath so fully confuted himself in several places.</p>
            <p>Yet lest through the want of a <hi>reply to them,</hi> his <hi>pupils</hi> and <hi>Proselites</hi> should take him for an infallible Oracle, an <hi>irrefragable Doctor,</hi> and so conclude their <hi>Champion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible.</hi> Though in our own sight we are but as <hi>little David,</hi> in comparison of this great <hi>Goliah,</hi> for our scola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick parts, and <hi>polemique abilities.</hi> We have adventured to appear against him, after his <hi>fourth edition,</hi> or appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the field <hi>without opposition.</hi> And whether we have not cut off the <hi>head</hi> of this <hi>great Champion</hi> with his <hi>own Sword,</hi> we leave to the judgement of the Reader and Spectator.</p>
            <p>Be pleased also (Courteous Reader) to take notice, that had there been as free a passage for <hi>Truth</hi> as there is for <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> and that the <hi>Men</hi> of this <hi>Generation</hi> exceeded not the <hi>Prelates</hi> for their strict <hi>suppression</hi> of the <hi>presse;</hi> we had not onely followed him at the <hi>heeles of his first Edition,</hi> but many more able <hi>Combatants</hi> had got through the <hi>Presse</hi> into the <hi>field</hi> against him, and long since laid him flat on his back, and broke the neck of his <hi>Printing pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But seeing the <hi>divine providence</hi> hath through much <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty</hi> brought this discourse to thy hand, wherein we have <hi>discharged our Consciences</hi> in a faithfull discovery
<pb facs="tcp:165546:4"/> of the <hi>unlawfulnesse and inexpediency of subscribing</hi> this <hi>new Engagement,</hi> and have answered the most <hi>material</hi> pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages <hi>in Mr. DURIES Considerations and just Repropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salls</hi> to the contrary, in which is included an Answer to the other forenamed <hi>Scriblers</hi> after his Copy. We leave it to thy <hi>serious perusall,</hi> beseeching thee to <hi>consider what we have said;</hi> and the <hi>good Lord,</hi> who is the <hi>Father of lights,</hi> give thee <hi>a discerning spirit</hi> in these times, wherein men are <hi>given up unto strong delusions for detaining the Truth in unrighteousness.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>VALE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165546:4"/>
            <head>A PACK OF PURITANS MAINTAINING The unlawfulnesse, and unexpediency of subscribing the <hi>New Engagement;</hi> and professing the dissatisfaction of their Judgements, and unresolvednesse of their tender Consciences. With Mr. <hi>John Dury</hi> his CONSIDERATIONS and JUST RE-PROPOSALS concerning it.</head>
            <p>THough we delight not to revive that odious, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull name of <hi>Puritan,</hi> with which in the height of <hi>Prelacy</hi> and <hi>Prerogative Royal,</hi> all conscientious men were stigmatized, that scrupled <hi>Conformity</hi> to supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Innovations</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and opposed illegal <hi>Taxations</hi> and <hi>Impositions</hi> in the <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet when we do consider, how that all those unhappy <hi>Commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> that have been in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> to the subversion of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> are charged upon <hi>all the zealous Professours</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> under the Notion of the <note n="*" place="margin">The case of the King stated.</note>
               <hi>Puritan Faction.</hi> Because of the <hi>unjustifiable</hi> Proceedings of some, both against the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> whose sinnes (we professe) have been, and still are the matters of our <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>shame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, lest that all that do professe the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and are carefull to keep a good <hi>Conscience, void of offence both towards God and Man,</hi> should for the <hi>miscarriages</hi> of some <hi>Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours,</hi> be condemned for <hi>a Packe of seditious, dissembling Hipocrites and</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">As they are in the Bish▪ of Downs Speech against Puritans, which hath been published in severall languages to the world.</note>
               <hi>Knaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:165546:5"/>
            <p>We have chosen rather in these perillous Times, to professe our selves <hi>A Packe of Puritans;</hi> and to testifie, that we are so far <hi>from having any Fellowship with those unfruitfull Works of Darknesse,</hi> which have been committed in the light of the Sun, to the <hi>dishonour</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> that we do <hi>reprove</hi> them rather; and as an <hi>evidence</hi> of our dislike of their <hi>Transactions,</hi> do publish the <hi>Grounds</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> for our <hi>non-subscription</hi> to this <hi>new Engagement</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>But before we begin, we shall, <hi>as in the presence of the Searcher of all hearts,</hi> professe and demonstrate; That the <hi>Grounds</hi> of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulging what we have conceived of the <hi>unlawfulnesse</hi> and <hi>unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diency</hi> of this <hi>new Engagement</hi> negatively, are not, To create unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary <hi>Scruples</hi> and <hi>Fears</hi> in other mens heads and hearts, or facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and maliciously to kindle a <hi>Fire</hi> to destroy the common wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of this Land of our Nativity; but positively, according to our duty as <hi>Saints,</hi> to <hi>preserve</hi> the <hi>Souls</hi> of our <hi>Brethren</hi> from the <hi>ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>of a good Conscience,</hi> upon the Rockes of <hi>unrighteousnesse, Disloyalty</hi> and <hi>Perjury. In Mr. Dury's Dialect. Just Repr. pag.</hi> 20. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>To uncase our selves, and propound our Doubts.</hi> By which, to <hi>provoke</hi> Master <hi>Dury</hi> or any other, to give better satisfaction to our <hi>tender Consciences,</hi> than what we have yet received. And to <hi>evidence</hi> to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the World, that when we are called out to suffer <hi>Proscription</hi> and <hi>non-protection</hi> for our <hi>non-subscription,</hi> we expose not our selves to suffering either through <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>arrogance;</hi> not because we are <hi>contentious,</hi> but because we are <hi>conscientious,</hi> and dare not sin to keep our selves from suffering.</p>
            <p>We do indeed <hi>professe</hi> to all the World, that when we parted so liberally with our <hi>Estates,</hi> to <hi>preserve</hi> our <hi>Propriety</hi> in them, as also to <hi>purchase</hi> that <hi>Liberty</hi> for our <hi>Consciences,</hi> that nothing might be <hi>urged</hi> upon them <hi>contrary to the revealed will of God;</hi> we could not imagine that when we were delivered out of the danger of it, from our <hi>professed Enemies,</hi> we should be exposed to it by our <hi>professed Friends.</hi> But as now we see our folly, in looking <hi>to live godly in Christ Jesus,</hi> without <hi>Persecution,</hi> and to go to <hi>Heaven</hi> a new way, and not <hi>through many tribulations;</hi> so we do unfeignedly desire to humble our selves under the <hi>Almighty hand of our God,</hi> who is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to <hi>curse</hi> our <hi>Blessings,</hi> and to use those as Rods in his hand for our <hi>correction;</hi> from whom we expected in our most <hi>precise</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165546:5"/>
               <hi>circumspect</hi> walking, both countenance, incouragement, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. And now through the strength of <hi>Christ</hi> do resolve to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny our selves, to take up his <hi>Crosse,</hi> to suffer rather than sin.</p>
            <p>We must needs say, that we are not in this juncture of time without some such suggestions from our very good <hi>Friends,</hi> and near Relations; as our <hi>Saviour</hi> had sometimes from <hi>Peter,</hi> for to <hi>spare</hi> and <hi>pity</hi> our selves, that none of those miserable Evils may come upon Us, our Wives, and Children, which necessarily will be the fruit of our <hi>non-subscription.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And would we be guided by <hi>President</hi> rather than by <hi>Precept,</hi> we have the Examples of too many <hi>Professours</hi> before us; That to keep themselves from the <hi>winde</hi> of <hi>Persecution,</hi> and <hi>Affliction,</hi> for keeping a good <hi>Conscience,</hi> can set their <hi>Consciences</hi> as <hi>Diogenes</hi> boasted, he could set his <hi>Barrell</hi> in which he lived, <hi>any way to keep out the winde.</hi> But we have learned to be Followers of others (though eminent for <hi>Profession</hi>) no further than they are Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of <hi>Christ Jesus:</hi> who though he knew how much it would prejudice him, not to comply with the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> in a seeming civil<note place="margin">Matth. 15. 2. 11 Mark 7. 5. Ephes. 5. 11. Prov. 1. 10. Isai 8. 12. Rev. 18. 4. 1 Thess. 4. 1. Mal. 10. 28.</note> Action of <hi>washing his hands,</hi> yet he not onely refused it, but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> it, as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> testifie.</p>
            <p>But this being our indispensible Duty, <hi>To have no fellowship with the unfruitfull workes of darknesse;</hi> not <hi>to consent with sinners when they entice us;</hi> neither <hi>to say, a Confederacy, a Confederacy,</hi> with them, though they should enforce us.</p>
            <p>We dare not through a base and slavish <hi>fear of men,</hi> be drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>a sinfull Engagement,</hi> or <hi>Confederacy</hi> with them; and that <hi>not onely</hi> lest we should <hi>thereby pertake of their sinnes,</hi> and so <hi>of their punishments:</hi> but also lest that we should <hi>dishonour</hi> our most <hi>holy Profession,</hi> and testifie that we are <hi>such</hi> as do <hi>fear them that can kill the body,</hi> more than <hi>him that can cast both body and soul into hell-fire.</hi> Such as have but little love unto our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Master,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had rather that his <hi>Gospel</hi> should <hi>suffer,</hi> than our selves; such as have but little <hi>Faith</hi> in Gods <hi>All-sufficiency,</hi> and therefore will use sinfull <hi>shifts</hi> to <hi>preserve</hi> our selves from a suffering condition; such as are <hi>inordinate lovers of our selves, and of the world.</hi> And that we answer not the end of our <hi>Redemption through the pretious</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 23.</note>
               <hi>bloud of Jesus Christ, who hath bought us with a price,</hi> that we should
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165546:6"/> not be the sinfull <hi>Servants</hi> of Men, by any sinfull Compliance<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 23.</note> whatsoever.</p>
            <p>Upon all which <hi>Premises,</hi> which we have seriously weighed in our most deliberate thoughts, and have closely laid to our awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Consciences: we must <hi>professe,</hi> that we cannot, we dare not, by <hi>Subscription,</hi> or any other way whatsoever, testifie our <hi>assent</hi> unto any sinfull <hi>Engagement</hi> or <hi>Confederacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, because that we know it will be here objected. What? Do you look upon this <hi>Engagement</hi> imposed by the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> of the Nation, <hi>viz. To be true and faithfull to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now established, without a King and House of Lords:</hi> as a sinfull <hi>Engargement?</hi> If you consult with <hi>Mr. John Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> you shall finde, that to <hi>subscribe</hi> this <hi>Engagement</hi> is an <hi>Indispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Duty,</hi> and that you are bound <hi>to subscribe it by your Covenant,</hi> and other sacred Oaths which you have taken (<hi>vide. Consider. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the present Engagement, pag. 16 line 17. pag. 6. line 18. pag. 9. line</hi> 23.)</p>
            <p>For answer to this, We do in the sincerity of our hearts <hi>professe,</hi> That we should have looked upon it as matter of much compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and joy, (both in relation to other mens sins, and our own sufferings) if we could have found <hi>Mr. Dury's Confirmations</hi> to have been as clear, as his <hi>Affirmations</hi> are confident; and that upon our serious search that we have made into this present <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> we could have given as fair a <hi>Character</hi> of it, as the <hi>Apostle</hi> doth of the <hi>Commandment;</hi> That it is <hi>holy, just, and good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But seeing to the grief of our hearts, we have found it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; and that therefore we cannot <hi>subscribe</hi> it without <hi>wounding our Consciences;</hi> we shall for the Reasons already propounded, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate the <hi>Grounds</hi> upon which this present <hi>Engagement</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares unto us to be both <hi>unlawfull</hi> and <hi>unexpedient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpose, we shall do these two things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, Propose as considerable; when Engagements, and what En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements in general are sinfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Expose this particular Engagement to Examination; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sinfull or no, by the aforesaid Consideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the clearing of the former; <hi>what Engagements, or when En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, or Confederacies are sinfull?</hi> We conceive that to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165546:6"/> or to engage our selves, or to be in <hi>Confederacy</hi> with others, is not simply sinfull in it selfe; but according as it is <hi>circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated,</hi> it may not onely be sinfull, but be very much <hi>aggravated.</hi> For although <hi>Circumstances</hi> are <hi>inconsiderable</hi> in Relation unto <hi>natural</hi> bodies in <hi>Philosophy:</hi> yet even <hi>Circumstances,</hi> they are the <hi>Essentials</hi> of <hi>moral</hi> Actions in <hi>Theology,</hi> and they do give the <hi>formality</hi> of <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> good or evil, to such things or Actions which are in their own <hi>Nature</hi> but <hi>indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be demanded then, <hi>What are those Circumstances which make</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Engagements sinfull?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We answer, that though there be but two <hi>Circumstances</hi> in all <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answer. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>natural</hi> things, the <hi>ubi</hi> and the <hi>quando.</hi> Every created <hi>natural</hi> being, is somewhere, and at sometime: yet in <hi>Morality</hi> there are more, as the <hi>quis, quid, ubi, quibus atque cui, cur, quomodo, quando.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Most of which <hi>Circumstances,</hi> applied to <hi>Engagements</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> will render them to be exceeding sinfull: if we do consider either the <hi>quis,</hi> who it is that doth <hi>engage</hi> himselfe or others; the <hi>quid,</hi> the matter of the <hi>Engagement</hi> it selfe; the <hi>quibus atque cui,</hi> the Persons with whom, or to whom we do <hi>engage</hi> our selves; the <hi>cur,</hi> the end wherefore we do enter such <hi>Engagements;</hi> and the <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo,</hi> the manner of our entering into <hi>Engagements</hi> and <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here, as we are <hi>Bible-bearing Puritans,</hi> we could at large<note place="margin">Matth. 14. 7. Matth. 26. 72. Acts 23. 21. 2 Sam. 15. 12. Num. 30 Josh. 2. 17. Eccles. 9. 2. Gen. 24. 5. 8.</note> demonstrate from the <hi>Scriptures Engagements</hi> to be sinfull for the <hi>quid,</hi> or the matter of them, when they are not onely unlawfull, but inexpedient. To be sinfull in respect of the <hi>quis</hi> and <hi>quibus,</hi> when if a publike <hi>Engagement</hi> be <hi>prescribed</hi> by those who have no lawfull <hi>Authority</hi> over them that are to <hi>subscribe,</hi> or when <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed</hi> by those who have no power over themselves, because <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged</hi> already. To be sinfull in regard of the <hi>cur</hi> or the <hi>quare,</hi> The end wherefore we enter inter into such <hi>Engagements</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies;</hi> as when 'tis to <hi>confirme</hi> and <hi>ratifie</hi> former Acts of <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, Injustice,</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and is not like to be an end of <hi>strife</hi> and <hi>contention,</hi> but rather to make <hi>strife</hi> and <hi>contention</hi> to be end lesse. And also in respect of the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>engaging,</hi> when we do it <hi>rashly</hi> without taking counsel of God, <hi>incautelously</hi> without serious and mature deliberation with our selves, <hi>ignorantly</hi> without true
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165546:7"/> information of the nature of it, and <hi>doubtingly,</hi> without full satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 13.</note> to our Consciences, of the lawfulnesse of it.</p>
            <p>But we conceive, that by this light touch <hi>in transitu,</hi> we have sufficiently demonstrated what we proposed in the first place; to wit, <hi>when</hi> or <hi>what Engagements in general</hi> are sinfull.</p>
            <p>Now therefore that we or others may not enter upon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>engagement ignorantly, rashly, doubtingly,</hi> or <hi>incautelously,</hi> we shall proceed to <hi>expose</hi> this <hi>particular engagement,</hi> which is to be <hi>imposed</hi> upon us unto the <hi>Trial,</hi> by those <hi>Circumstances</hi> we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready tendred to <hi>Consideration;</hi> which do render <hi>engagements to be sinfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the first place therefore, we shall consider of the <hi>quid,</hi> or the <hi>matter</hi> of this present <hi>Absolute,</hi> and <hi>positive Promise</hi> or <hi>Engagement: To be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now established without a King or House of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before we come to determine of the <hi>matter</hi> of this <hi>engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> whether it be <hi>unlawfull</hi> or <hi>unexpedient,</hi> we shall briefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve this Question:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When an Act may be concluded to be unlawfull or unexpedient?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Answer</hi> to this in short; A thing is then materially <hi>unlawfull,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> when <hi>contrary</hi> unto the <hi>holy Law of God,</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Perfection</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> or secondly, when <hi>contrary</hi> unto such wholesome and truly constituted <hi>Laws of the Land</hi> in which we live, which are not <hi>repugnant</hi> to the <hi>Laws of God.</hi> And a thing is then <hi>unexpedient</hi> (though <hi>lawfull</hi>) when either we cannot come to the <hi>Good</hi> in it, unlesse we do that which is <hi>evil;</hi> or when the thing <hi>done,</hi> or to be <hi>done,</hi> is not like to <hi>bring</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Crad. <hi>Gosp. li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, 63. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Glory to God,</hi> and his <hi>Gospel, advantage</hi> to others, or <hi>benefit</hi> to our own selves.</p>
            <p>Now this being <hi>premised,</hi> we must needs conclude, till better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, notwithstanding what we have from <hi>Mr. Dury;</hi> That to <hi>engage</hi> our selves to be <hi>true and faithfull to the Common-wealth of England,</hi> is sinfull, because <hi>unlawfull,</hi> in some kinde in both senses; as <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>wholesome Laws of this Kingdom,</hi> agreeing with the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and so consequentially <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Law of God</hi> also▪</p>
            <p>We finde indeed <hi>Mr. Dury</hi> often mentioning the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> in his Discourse, <hi>p.</hi> 4, 6. to which he saith, <hi>We are bound to be true and faithfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165546:7"/>
            <p>Now as we apprehend his meaning by the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> to be the <hi>welfare</hi> of all <hi>degrees</hi> and <hi>conditions</hi> of men within the three Kingdomes, which is implied in severall passages of his, when he saith, <hi>The Common-wealth was in the bosom of the Kingdom, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsical</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>From. M.</hi> Dury's <hi>Pen, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pro. p. 13.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>with it.</hi> We conceive it not simply <hi>unlawfull, faithfully</hi> to seek its <hi>welfare.</hi> But it is <hi>evident</hi> both by the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Act <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing,</hi> and also by the <hi>expresse Letter</hi> of the <hi>engagement,</hi> that by the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> is meant <hi>A State of Government,</hi> contradistinct un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Monarchy; without a King and House of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now under this <hi>consideration,</hi> the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>Engagement</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares <hi>unlawfull;</hi> and that first, because we are told by the skilfull in Lavv, <hi>It is absolutely against the Laws of the Land.</hi> For by this <hi>Engagement</hi> to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> we oblige our selves to yield that <hi>fealty</hi> and <hi>homage</hi> to our <hi>fellow Subjects,</hi> which is due unto the King onely, as is very clear, in <hi>Cooks Instit. p.</hi> 64, 65, 66, 67. And therefore is no lesse than <hi>Treason</hi> within the <hi>Statute of 25 Edw. 3. chap.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>engaging</hi> to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> as a <hi>Government,</hi> is consequentially <hi>unlawfull</hi> by the <hi>Law of God,</hi> because it tends to the <hi>abolishing</hi> of a long settled <hi>Government</hi> amongst us by the <hi>Law of the Land,</hi> which is also agreeable, and no way <hi>contrary</hi> unto the <hi>Law of God,</hi> but rather <hi>Gods especial Ordinance, Deut. 17. 14, 15. Prov.</hi> 15. 16. prophesied of, and promised as a great blessing to the Church in <hi>Gospel</hi> times. To which <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> vve are not onely obliged <hi>to submit for the Lords sake, as agreeable to his will, 1 Pet.</hi> 13. 14, 15, 17. but also <hi>to pray for it in the first place, 1 Tim. 6. 15. That under it, we may lead a peaceable life, in all godlinesse and honesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the next place, suppose that this <hi>Engagement</hi> for the <hi>matter</hi> vvere <hi>lawfull,</hi> yet if the <hi>matter</hi> of it appear <hi>unexpedient,</hi> there vvill be <hi>Ground</hi> enough for us that do <hi>professe</hi> the <hi>Gospel,</hi> to take heed of <hi>subscribing it;</hi> such as vve are, must be carefull, that vvhat vve do <hi>hath no appearance of evil in it, that it be honest in the sight of all men, that it be of good report;</hi> that vvhat vve do, for the <hi>matter</hi> of it be not onely <hi>lawfull,</hi> but <hi>expedient; 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 23. That vvhat vve do may bring <hi>Glory to God, Honour to the Gospel, advantage to others, and benefit to our selves;</hi> and that, for the obtaining of that vvhich is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165546:8"/>
               <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>lawfull,</hi> vve do not that vvhich is <hi>sinfull</hi> and <hi>evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Novv the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>engagement</hi> being brought unto this <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> vvill not onely appear <hi>unlawfull</hi> but <hi>inexpedient,</hi> To <hi>engage</hi> our selves to be true and faithfull to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> as novv esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished.</p>
            <p>For first, suppose to <hi>abolish Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>to be faithfull to the Common-wealth as now established</hi> vvere <hi>lawfull,</hi> yet considering vve cannot come at it vvithout manifest <hi>Perjury</hi> (of vvhich more by and by) to our selves, and by giving our <hi>consent</hi> to all those sinfull and indirect meanes, by vvhich the said <hi>Government</hi> vvas founded, and to this day supported; it must needs be <hi>inexpedient</hi> for us to <hi>subscribe</hi> it, and vve cannot do it vvithout being <hi>accessary</hi> unto the sins of <hi>others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hovv <hi>Mr. Dury</hi> hath ansvvered this <hi>material Argument</hi> against the <hi>engagement,</hi> as vve finde no satisfaction to our <hi>Consciences</hi> in it, so we leave it to the judgement of his best Friends, whether it will passe for the appearance of an Answer; for saith he, <hi>Pag. 6. l. 1. Here I perceive is the thing which doth pinch you in the businesse, you thinke that they that made the change in Government, broke the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and if you engage under this change, you break your Covenant also, and make your selfe accessary to their guilt, Pa. 5. li. ult.</hi> To which I shall say, that <hi>I see not how it will appear, that the consequence at all doth follow, although they that made the change should be guilty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now had <hi>Mr. Dury</hi> given any Argument or Scripture ground to satisfie us or any other, we should have rejoyced in the sight of it. But because <hi>Mr. Dury</hi> is so dim-sighted, and cannot see how such a <hi>Consequence</hi> will follow, <hi>That if we do subscribe this engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> we shall make our selves <hi>accessary</hi> unto the sinnes of others, we will helpe him to a little spiritual eye-salve in these following <hi>Reasons</hi> or <hi>Arguments:</hi> First, if to bid others <hi>God speed</hi> in an evil Work, makes us <hi>Partakers of their sinnes, 2 John</hi> 5. 11. And to have a hand unadvisedly in bringing in an unworthy <hi>Person</hi> into a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Office, makes us <hi>Partakers</hi> of those sinnes they shall commit in it, as the <hi>Apostle</hi> implies, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22? Then deliberately <hi>to engage</hi> our selves to the support of this <hi>Government</hi> sinfully established, must needs make us <hi>accessary</hi> to the sinnes of others in it, it being the highest <hi>Consent</hi> with others in sin that can be.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:165546:8"/>
            <p>Secondly, if to allow of the sinfull wayes of others, onely by our <hi>presence</hi> with them, involves us in their guilt, <hi>Acts</hi> 22. 20. And to <hi>favour</hi> those that do <hi>evil,</hi> be as great a Crime, as to commit the sin it selfe, <hi>Because it makes our damnation just, Rom.</hi> 1. 32. Then to <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe</hi> this <hi>engagement,</hi> which testifies our <hi>approbation</hi> of the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished <hi>Government,</hi> with the meanes by which it was effected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> must needs make us <hi>accessary</hi> to the sinnes of others.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, seeing that without sinning our selves, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting the guilt of other mens sinnes, we cannot <hi>subscribe</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Account,</hi> though the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>engagement</hi> should be <hi>lawfull,</hi> yet it is <hi>inexpedient;</hi> We cannot come to <hi>enjoy</hi> it without <hi>committing of evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But suppose in respect of the <hi>quid,</hi> or the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> that it were not <hi>unlawfull,</hi> to <hi>engage</hi> our selves to the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> in <hi>opposition</hi> to <hi>Monarchy,</hi> nor yet <hi>inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient</hi> upon the <hi>former Ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, if it appear so upon the <hi>latter,</hi> that the <hi>subscribing</hi> of the <hi>engagement</hi> be like to be so farre from bringing <hi>honour</hi> to the <hi>Gospel, advantage</hi> to others, and <hi>profit</hi> to our selves, that the <hi>fruits</hi> of it are like to be otherwise altogether. It will be <hi>inexpedient</hi> for us to <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe,</hi> and consequently sinfull.</p>
            <p>Now that we may not with <hi>Mr. Dury</hi> confidently affirme, but <hi>prove nothing</hi> (as he doth <hi>P.</hi> 18.) about the <hi>expediency</hi> of the <hi>engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that it is a duty that relates <hi>to the whole Common-wealth, the safety of all, and our own necessary Peace and Preservation, lin.</hi> 35. We shall not onely <hi>affirme,</hi> that <hi>to subscribe</hi> this <hi>engagement</hi> will be <hi>inexpedient,</hi> as it will bring forth <hi>dishonour</hi> and a scandall upon the <hi>Gospel.</hi> Secondly, extreme perill and prejudice <hi>to the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> Thirdly, unconceivable damage unto every particular <hi>Subscriber;</hi> but we shall <hi>confirme</hi> it by many clear and evident <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>to subscribe</hi> this <hi>engagement</hi> for to establish a <hi>Polarchy</hi> or <hi>Popular Government,</hi> and <hi>to abolish Royal Dignity,</hi> will be so farre from <hi>honouring</hi> the <hi>Gospel,</hi> as that we shall bring a great scandall upon it, and <hi>dishonour our most holy Profession.</hi> And that first, as it will <hi>justifie</hi> all those who have been <hi>accounted</hi> traducers of <hi>Puritans,</hi> as <hi>enemies to Monarchy,</hi> that this was looked upon as an intolerable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165546:9"/>
               <hi>calumny,</hi> we finde in <hi>Mr. Case</hi> his <hi>Sermon before the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, 26. Octob. 1642. Pa.</hi> 11, 12. where he hath these words, <hi>It is and hath been from ancient times the cursed Policy of desperate malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Courtiers and Counsellers, when they would arme Princes and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates against the poor People of God, to possesse their eares and hearts with this prejudice, That they are enemies to Monarchy. And</hi> saith he, <hi>Doth not these</hi> Rehums <hi>and</hi> Shimshies <hi>fill our Kings royal eares with this</hi> Odium, <hi>that the Parliament and Puritans are enemies to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and intend nothing but to bring all into a Parity, and after they have pulled down Bishop, then down with King too; with a world of such Calumnies invented by the father of lyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now <hi>to subscribe</hi> this <hi>engagement</hi> against <hi>Monarchy,</hi> would make it appear, that such <hi>Assertions</hi> were no unjust <hi>aspersions.</hi> But that they said truly in charging <hi>Puritans</hi> with <hi>a designe of altering, and subverting the Government of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>subscribing</hi> of the <hi>engagement</hi> would <hi>dishonour</hi> the <hi>Gospel;</hi> as it would bring an odious scandall upon the <hi>Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> in the Church to which we are by <hi>Covenant</hi> obliged. And that, as it would ratifie a Prelatical <hi>Aphorisme,</hi> which we alwayes looked upon as a stumbling blocke in the way, devised <hi>to hinder the Reformation of the Church, No Bishop no King, no Miter no Scepter.</hi> As if so be, there could be no real <hi>Reformation</hi> in the Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Regal extirpation</hi> in the State.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, <hi>to subscribe</hi> this <hi>Engagement</hi> will be <hi>inexpedient</hi> and scandalous, as it may <hi>nullifie</hi> all those <hi>Apologies</hi> which have been made in the behalfe of <hi>Professours:</hi> that much hath been said for them is very evident, as by many publike Writings <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>A plea for the innocent, in</hi> Q. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>time, 1602. A Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Puritans 1641.</hi>
               </note> for their Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication; <hi>That the Ministers and People falsly called Puritans, were injuriously slandered, for enemies to Regal Government, and for Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of the State.</hi> So that, by what hath been from time to time so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly professed by the <hi>zealous Desirers of Reformation,</hi> when ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniated by the Prelates: but now for such <hi>to subscribe</hi> this <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,</hi> the end whereof is <hi>Eradication of Monarchical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> will render all those <hi>Apologies</hi> to be false, hypocritical, and void; and that what was then said in their behalfes, was onely to keep them from crushing, till they had ability or an <hi>oportunity</hi> to turn the <hi>Kingdom</hi> up-side down:</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:165546:9"/>
            <p>So that now, upon these <hi>Considerations</hi> it is evident, that <hi>to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe</hi> this <hi>Engagement</hi> would be <hi>inexpedient,</hi> as it would bring <hi>dishonour</hi> to the <hi>Gospel,</hi> and a great scandall upon the <hi>zealous Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours of Religion,</hi> and them onely.</p>
            <p>But in the next place, as we cannot <hi>subscribe</hi> without much <hi>dishonour to God, the Gospel, and Religion we professe.</hi> Secondly, not without extreme perill and prejudice unto the <hi>whole Common-wealth,</hi> unto all <hi>degrees, rankes,</hi> and <hi>conditions</hi> of men in the three <hi>Kingdomes:</hi> first, <hi>to subscribe, To be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth as now established without a King,</hi> would be extremely injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and prejudicial unto the <hi>Supreme Magistrate of the Kingdom,</hi> who notwithstanding his <hi>forcible expulsion</hi> and <hi>dis-possession</hi> is not <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested</hi> of that <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> he hath unto the <hi>English Throne.</hi> Now if it were a sin so <hi>provoking</hi> in a <hi>King, for to take away his Subjects Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> because <hi>the inheritance of his father:</hi> What is it then for a <hi>subject to take away the inheritance of a King from him?</hi> which is <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually done,</hi> in taking this <hi>Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to subscribe this Engagement, to be true and faithfull to the Commonwealth as now established, <hi>without an House of Lords;</hi> would be prejudicious and injurious to the Nobles of the Land, and deprive them of their <hi>Birth-rights:</hi> which is to sit in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and as one of the three Estates, to be <hi>Legislators,</hi> and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate with King and Commons. Now, by <hi>subscribing this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,</hi> we dis-inherit and dis-seize them of their <hi>Right,</hi> and that with the greatest wrong and injustice that may be; because, <hi>exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded without a lawfull judgement, or Triall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, to subscribe <hi>to be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth,</hi> as a <hi>Government</hi> contradistinct unto <hi>Monarchy</hi> will be <hi>inexpedient;</hi> because not onely unprofitable, but prejudiciall, perilous, and of dangerous consequence to the whole <hi>Commonwealth</hi> in generall; For, upon the former grounds, the <hi>Heir and Successour,</hi> with the <hi>Nobility of the Land,</hi> being thus <hi>unjustly</hi> and <hi>violently</hi> dispossest of <hi>their Right,</hi> and Barracadoed from <hi>re-entering</hi> by this <hi>sinfull engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> it must needs bring upon <hi>the Kingdome,</hi> not onely a <hi>priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of that <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> which we had with other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, making us who were the <hi>Head,</hi> the chief among the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to become the <hi>Tail,</hi> the puniest <hi>State</hi> in <hi>Christendom, dissolving</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:165546:10"/> all those ancient Leagues which were made with forreigne Princes for the Kingdomes good; and also <hi>the union between the three</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> But will <hi>positively</hi> involve us in <hi>perpetual Warres</hi> and <hi>Troubles.</hi> And through the maintenance of Armies, by <hi>intolerable Taxes</hi> and <hi>Impositions (transcendently</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding all former <hi>Monopolies</hi> and <hi>Ship-money</hi>) render us the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablest and slavishest People under Heaven; such as shall never know when we are secure, either in respect of our <hi>soul, body,</hi> or <hi>estate:</hi> for as we finde by experience, in reference <hi>to Impositions upon our Estates, that since the promise of Liberty to the People;</hi> whereas in the Kings Time <hi>that Dutch Devil of Excise was but attempted to be conjured up amongst us, in the Rule of the</hi> Keepers <hi>of our Liberties, it hath not onely been imposed, but in some things doubled and trebled.</hi> So in reference <hi>to Impositions upon the Conscience.</hi> Though at first the <hi>Engagement</hi> against <hi>Monarchy</hi> was onely <hi>imposed</hi> upon the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that divided the spoil of the</hi> Kingdom, and were in Offices of profit; yet it stayes not there, but is now <hi>to be enforced upon all.</hi> And what great <hi>Augur</hi> this little <hi>Wimble</hi> must make way for, as we know not, so peradventure not they themselves, whom by this <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription</hi> we should <hi>constitute</hi> to be our <hi>new</hi> and <hi>absolute Governours.</hi> For as <hi>necessity</hi> hath put them upon <hi>taking away the Life of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Country;</hi> so it may inforce them <hi>to impose</hi> upon us <hi>the Murder</hi> of our own <hi>natural,</hi> and <hi>spiritual Parents, if they will not comply, and be in Confederacy with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But besides all these, with many other Miseries which are like to come upon the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> with those horrid Injuries to the <hi>Chief</hi> and <hi>most noble Parts of the Body Politique, by subscribing this Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place, it will be so farre from procuring Peace and <hi>Preservation</hi> to every particular <hi>Subscriber,</hi> as <hi>Mr. Dury</hi> hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, <hi>Pa. 18. That it will bring unconceivable detriment and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage unto every individual Subscriber thereof.</hi> And that not onely as shall be <hi>instrumental,</hi> in <hi>putting on the yoak of intolerable slavery upon his own necke with his own hands,</hi> but also of <hi>rivetting</hi> it fast (by <hi>the absolute and unlimited Engagement</hi>) from falling off. And as he shall by his <hi>transcendent Perjury</hi> expose himselfe and <hi>Posterity</hi> to perpetual Infamy, <hi>to the ruine of the outward man.</hi> But as he shall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165546:10"/> deprive himselfe of <hi>the inward Peace and tranquility of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> (and as it is reported of some <hi>Subscribers</hi> of this <hi>engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> already) be filled with <hi>life extinguishing</hi> horrors and terrors of <hi>Conscience.</hi> Besides the hazard of <hi>damnation to the immortal Soul,</hi> by <hi>subscribing</hi> unto an <hi>engagement,</hi> which for the <hi>matter</hi> of it is so <hi>contrary unto the Law of God, and of the Land,</hi> and through its <hi>inexpediency</hi> so scandalous, injurious, and perillous, as it appeares to be.</p>
            <p>But to all this it may be objected, <hi>That if there were no alleviati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>or palliation of what hath been propounded about the seeming unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse and inexpediency of this</hi> Engagement <hi>for the matter of it, by the</hi> Supreme Authority <hi>of the Power of imposing this</hi> Engagement, <hi>It would be then most</hi> dangerous <hi>and dreadfull to</hi> subscribe: <hi>but the</hi> Authority <hi>imposing this</hi> Engagement <hi>have legislative Power, not onely to declare what is lawfull, but to make things which are onely of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane concernment, to be lawfull and warrantable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in <hi>Answer</hi> to this <hi>Objection,</hi> we shall fall upon the <hi>Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> of the second particular <hi>Circumstance,</hi> which we propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the discovery of the sinfulnesse of an <hi>engagement,</hi> and that is the <hi>quis,</hi> relating to <hi>the Persons engaging</hi> or <hi>to be engaged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before that we begin to consider of the <hi>quis,</hi> in relation to the Power <hi>imposing the engagement,</hi> we shall a little examine what is said by <hi>Mr. Dury,</hi> against this present practice of ours; <hi>For</hi> (saith he, <hi>Pa. 9, 10.) as concerning the present Power, by which the</hi> Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>is tendered, whether it be an usurped Power;</hi> he affirmes, <hi>it doth not belong unto us to judge definitively of the Right which the Supreme Power over us in the world, pretend to have unto their Places; and the Reason</hi> (saith he) <hi>is this, because I finde it no part of the Profession of Christianity to meddle with this matter; nor do I see that God doth allow private men to take so much upon them over their Superiours,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Answer</hi> to this, in the first place, by way of Concession; though we grant, <hi>that in a constituted Government</hi> of as long stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as <hi>Monarchy</hi> hath been in <hi>Brittain,</hi> which hath been <hi>upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> 441 yeares before the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> as we finde<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Captain</hi> Audley Mervin's <hi>Speech.</hi>
               </note> proved by a <hi>Speech</hi> delivered in <hi>Parliament, May</hi> 24. 1641. and made so glorious and unquestionable by Antiquity: as when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by <hi>Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> yet had their <hi>Laws</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165546:11"/>
               <hi>Government</hi> unaltered; as we finde in the <hi>Lord Keepers Speech, Novemb.</hi> 3. 1640. Though under such a long continued <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> derived to us by our <hi>Ancestours.</hi> For a Subject by Birth to question the <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Supreme Magistrate</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, <hi>we cannot see that God doth allow private men to take so much upon them over their Superiours,</hi> because their <hi>Authority</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all dispute.</p>
            <p>Yet when a <hi>government</hi> is to be <hi>settled</hi> and <hi>constituted,</hi> while the <hi>Change</hi> of so long an <hi>established government</hi> is before our faces, and that by a Power so <hi>disputable</hi> as this is; it is our duty, and we are bound as <hi>Christians,</hi> by the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> before we do <hi>engage</hi> our selves to be in <hi>subjection</hi> to any such Power, to satisfie our selves concerning their <hi>lawfull Authority</hi> to rule over us. For though as <hi>Mr. Dury</hi> doth urge, that the Rule of <hi>Subjects</hi> behaviour, as <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> is clearly determined, <hi>Rom. 13. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 13, 14. Tit. 3. 1. To be for conscience sake, and because Gods Ordinance, Pa.</hi> 11. yet we <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> that <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Ʋsurpation</hi> is none of Gods <hi>Ordinance;</hi> and it <hi>concernes Christians</hi> to be satisfied whether it be <hi>to a lawfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate</hi> they do <hi>engage</hi> themselves, or unto <hi>Jacke Straw,</hi> or <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden;</hi> and this we are to do in obedience to Gods Command, by which we are obliged to yield <hi>Obedience to the lawfull Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, Commandment</hi> the <hi>fifth.</hi> But also <hi>forbidden to engage</hi> our selves to <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to those that are no <hi>lawfull Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates.</hi> For this is one Rule given by all <hi>Divines,</hi> in expounding the <hi>moral Law,</hi> That <hi>positive Precepts</hi> do imply and injoyn <hi>negative Duties,</hi> as we must <hi>honour our Fathers,</hi> and <hi>governours,</hi> with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> so we are by the same <hi>Precept forbidden</hi> to honour such as are not our <hi>lawfull Rulers</hi> and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but <hi>Ʋsurpers.</hi> When the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Israel</hi> are like unto them that remove, <hi>Hos.</hi> 5. 10. We must take heed of <hi>walking wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly after their commandment with Ephraim, vers.</hi> 11. lest when we are oppressed and broken in judgement, we may thanke our selves.</p>
            <p>And now having thus cleared the way to our Worke, and having made it appear to be our duty in this juncture of time, though <hi>private Persons,</hi> to question the <hi>quis</hi> or the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribers of this present Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:165546:11"/>
            <p>We should proceed to <hi>discover</hi> the <hi>Grounds</hi> of our <hi>dis-satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> about <hi>subscribing the Engagement,</hi> in relation to the <hi>quis,</hi> the <hi>Persons prescribing,</hi> or <hi>imposing</hi> it. But knowing the <hi>Times</hi> to be so very <hi>perillous,</hi> that we must be made offenders for a word, and that to speak <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>reason,</hi> is like to be adjudged <hi>Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We shall onely say, that if in <hi>Ʋtopia,</hi> the <hi>Supreme Authority</hi> should consist of <hi>three Estates in Senate,</hi> assembled; a <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> (though <hi>engaged</hi> by severall <hi>sacred Obligations,</hi> to preserve the said <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi>) should by the assistance of a <hi>rebellious</hi> Army raised for the defence thereof, <hi>exclude</hi> the <hi>major</hi> part of the said <hi>Commons,</hi> and having <hi>declared</hi> themselves <hi>The onely Supreme Authority of Ʋtopia,</hi> should destroy and take away the life of <hi>their King, and abolish both the Estates of King and Lords;</hi> and although by the known Law of <hi>Vtopia,</hi> the said <hi>Commons</hi> have no power <hi>to impose</hi> upon the said <hi>Vtopians (pre-engaged</hi> to be true and faithfull to the <hi>King, his heirs, successours, and kingly govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) an <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Engagement, To be true to their New Government established, without a King or House of Lords,</hi> though it hath been done <hi>by force,</hi> and without <hi>their consent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this case, we may boldly say, that the said <hi>engagement,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>quis,</hi> the <hi>Prescribers</hi> or <hi>Imposers</hi> of it, is altogether <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull;</hi> and that because the <hi>Engagers</hi> of the said <hi>Vtopians,</hi> are onely a <hi>selfe-created Power,</hi> and so far, from being <hi>The Supreme Authority of that Nation,</hi> which consists of <hi>three Estates,</hi> as that they are not a <hi>third</hi> part of one of them, <hi>the Commons;</hi> and also so far from having any <hi>Authority to impose</hi> the said <hi>engagement</hi> upon their fellow <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> as that they have no <hi>Authority</hi> by the <hi>Vtopian</hi> Law to administer any <hi>Oath whatsoever.</hi> And if so, then not to <hi>impose an Oath</hi> or <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> for fealty to themselves, contrary to all those <hi>sacred Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</hi> by which they were bound <hi>to preserve the said Supreme Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in reference to our <hi>own case,</hi> to say any thing concerning the <hi>Authority of the Imposers</hi> of this present <hi>engagement,</hi> our mouthes being <hi>gagged,</hi> by two strong <hi>Instruments</hi> made this last year, <hi>we cannot.</hi> And therefore passing over the <hi>consideration</hi> of the <hi>quis,</hi> in relation to the <hi>Prescribers,</hi> we shall come to consider of the second <hi>Particular,</hi> proposed in reference to the <hi>quis,</hi> as it relates to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165546:12"/>
               <hi>Persons</hi> to be <hi>engaged,</hi> which are the <hi>Subscribers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As publike <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>engagements</hi> cannot be <hi>prescribed, or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully imposed,</hi> by those who have no power over <hi>others;</hi> so they cannot <hi>lawfully be subscribed</hi> by those who have no power over themselves. <hi>Qui non est sui juris, obligare se non potest.</hi> Which is the <hi>condition</hi> of all persons <hi>pre-engaged</hi> by former <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that this is the case of the whole Kingdom. If the <hi>Oaths</hi> of our <hi>Ancestours</hi> binde us as it did <hi>Saul,</hi> for the breach whereof God dealt so severely with his Family: or at least, of all those that ever <hi>took,</hi> either the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Supremacy, Allegiance,</hi> or of a <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> the <hi>Protestation,</hi> or the <hi>Covenant,</hi> we shall <hi>demonstrate</hi> in the proving of these two <hi>Assertions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, that this present <hi>engagement</hi> is <hi>contradictory,</hi> and strongly <hi>militates</hi> against the <hi>Oathes</hi> of <hi>Supremacy, Allegiance,</hi> and all those <hi>sacred Obligations</hi> before mentioned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that these <hi>sacred Oathes</hi> and <hi>Obligations</hi> are still bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Consciences</hi> of those that have taken them.</p>
            <p>First, the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>engagement,</hi> which is <hi>to be true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Common-wealth</hi> in opposition to <hi>Monarchy, without a King and House of Lords,</hi> is expresly contrary unto the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> which obligeth the Taker, not onely <hi>to bear faith and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the heires and successours</hi> of our late King, (of which more in another place) but also <hi>to defend their Crown and Dignity against all Conspiracies,</hi> which must needs be <hi>monarchical</hi> and <hi>kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> because that <hi>to defend their Crown or Dignity,</hi> is expressed <hi>distinctly</hi> from their <hi>Persons.</hi> So that to <hi>engage</hi> against <hi>kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> is <hi>point blanke</hi> contrary unto the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>engagement,</hi> is contrary unto the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> which bindes the Taker clearly and plainly, not onely <hi>to bear faith and true Allegiance to the Kings Highnesse, his Heires, and Successours; but to their power, to assist and defend all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictions, Priviledges, Preheminences, and Authorities granted</hi> unto the Kings Highnesse, his Heires, and Successours, or <hi>united and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now to <hi>establish Polarchy,</hi> and to <hi>abolish Monarchy,</hi> and to our power to <hi>assist</hi> and <hi>defend all Jurisdictions, Priviledges, Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minences,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:165546:12"/> and <hi>Authorities, united</hi> or <hi>annexed</hi> to the <hi>Imperial Crown,</hi> are as contrary as darknesse is to light.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is contrary to the Oath of a <hi>Free-man</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> which obligeth the Taker to be <hi>faithfull</hi> to such <hi>Heires,</hi> and <hi>Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours</hi> onely, as should wear the <hi>Imperial Crown,</hi> describing them either to be Kings or Queens. So that, though the <hi>Imposers</hi> of the <hi>Engagement</hi> should require our <hi>Allegiance,</hi> because <hi>de facto</hi> they are the Kings <hi>Successours</hi> in <hi>Government,</hi> yet being neither <hi>Kings</hi> nor Queens, we should violate this <hi>sacred</hi> Oath by this <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>matter</hi> of this <hi>engagement,</hi> as unto a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> without a <hi>King,</hi> is <hi>contrary</hi> unto our most <hi>Solemne Vow</hi> and <hi>Protestation, May</hi> 5. 1641. In which we have <hi>promised</hi> and <hi>vowed,</hi> unto▪ <hi>Almighty God, with our Lives, our Power, and Estates, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and defend,</hi> not onely the Kings <hi>Person,</hi> but his <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Estate;</hi> which <hi>Estate</hi> is not <hi>personally</hi> to be considered, but <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquely,</hi> in relation to his <hi>Government;</hi> because the defence of his <hi>Person</hi> is expresly provided for in the said <hi>Vow.</hi> Secondly, it is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> unto this <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Protestation,</hi> by which we are <hi>solemnly obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to maintain the Power and Priviledges of</hi> Parliament. Now it is the <hi>unqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stionable power and priviledge</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to have the King, if not <hi>personally,</hi> yet <hi>legally</hi> and <hi>politically</hi> present. And, it is his <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>estate,</hi> which by our <hi>Protestation</hi> we have <hi>promised to maintain</hi> and <hi>defend,</hi> to be the <hi>Supreme Estate,</hi> in that <hi>high Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>Engagement,</hi> as unto a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> without a King, is expresly <hi>contrary</hi> unto the <hi>Solemne Covenant</hi> we have taken: wherein we <hi>engaged sincerely, really,</hi> and <hi>constantly, to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Art. 3.</note>
               <hi>endeavour,</hi> and that with our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Estates to defend</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve</hi> not onely the Kings <hi>person,</hi> but his <hi>Authority.</hi> But now to be <hi>true and faithfull to a Common-wealth, contradistinct unto Regal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and with our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Estates to defend the Kings Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> are the greatest <hi>Contradictions</hi> that can be.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>to be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth, as now esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished without the House of Lords,</hi> is expresly <hi>contrary</hi> not onely to our aforesaid <hi>National Covenant,</hi> but to our <hi>Promise, Vow,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation▪</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 5. 1641. As being <hi>engaged</hi> by it <hi>to maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165546:13"/> the Power and Priviledges of Parliament,</hi> and by the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to preserve the Rights and Privilodges of Parliament.</hi> Now it being the <hi>Right, Power, and Priviledge of Parliament,</hi> to have the <hi>House of Lords</hi> as the onely <hi>Judicature</hi> in that <hi>Supreme Councel.</hi> But <hi>to subscribe</hi> the said <hi>Engagement</hi> is neither <hi>to maintain, defend, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve this undoubted Right, and Priviledge;</hi> but to give our <hi>consent</hi> to their <hi>extirpation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>to be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth, as it is now established,</hi> in a <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>forcible way,</hi> without the <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>free consent</hi> of the People, <hi>is contrary</hi> unto that part of our <hi>Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> which engageth us (in the former) <hi>to defend the lawfull Right and Liberty of the Subject,</hi> and <hi>to oppose</hi> all such as shall by <hi>force or conspiracy</hi> do any thing to the <hi>contrary,</hi> (and in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) <hi>to preserve the Liberties of the Kingdom,</hi> of the <hi>Right</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> is to be <hi>free,</hi> not onely from all <hi>Impositions</hi> upon their <hi>estates,</hi> (without their consent) but also upon their <hi>Consciences,</hi> by any <hi>Engagement,</hi> which may <hi>oblige</hi> them to yield <hi>obedience</hi> or <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gianee</hi> to such <hi>Persons,</hi> as by a <hi>selfe-created</hi> Power, shall <hi>assume the Government</hi> over them.</p>
            <p>And thus having now proved our first Assertion, <hi>that the matter of this Engagement is contradictory, and diametrically opposite to all our former oathes and sacred obligations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We shall proceed to the <hi>proof</hi> of the second, which we proposed: That these <hi>sacred Bonds and obligations</hi> do <hi>indispensibly</hi> binde the <hi>Consciences</hi> of men who have taken them.</p>
            <p>Now this we shall prove; first, from the consideration of the <hi>binding nature</hi> of an Oath in the general. Secondly, by considering these particular Oathes and Obligations.</p>
            <p>First, that any Oath that is <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>possible, indispensibly bindes the Conscience till the thing sworn be</hi> accomplished, appeareth upon this Ground, because that in every <hi>lawfull</hi> Oath there is a double <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation;</hi> one of Man to Man, the other of Man to God, whom <hi>in lifting up our hands unto,</hi> we not onely <hi>call</hi> to be a <hi>Witnesse</hi> of our sincere <hi>intentions</hi> to performe what we have sworn to Men, but to take <hi>revenge</hi> upon us if we be <hi>perfidious:</hi> and therefore we finde the Oath that passed between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> is called <hi>The Lords oath, 2 Sam, 21, 7. 1 Sam.</hi> 20. 6. And the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:165546:13"/> by which <hi>Subjects</hi> are bound to their <hi>Sovereigne,</hi> is called <hi>The oath of God, Eccles. 8. 2. I counsel thee</hi> (saith the Wise-man) <hi>to keep the Kings commandment, and that in regard of the oath of God.</hi> And therefore we have a Command from <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe, <hi>Thou shalt not forswear thy selfe, but shalt performe thy oath to the Lord.</hi> So that, we cannot be absolved in our <hi>Consciences</hi> from an Oath, no not by the Parties to whom we are sworne; because we are obliged in all <hi>lawfull</hi> Oathes <hi>to God,</hi> as well as <hi>Man;</hi> and he hath not onely commanded us <hi>to performe our oathes, Numb.</hi> 13. 3. but as he is a <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God,</hi> hath threatened, that he <hi>will not hold those guiltlesse that taketh his Name in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if all Oathes <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>possible</hi> are thus <hi>indispensibly bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> then it must needs follow, that all those particular Oathes and <hi>sacred obligations,</hi> which we have taken, do <hi>chain</hi> us by our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences,</hi> and do remain and abide at this present <hi>in full force, effect, and virtue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be <hi>objected,</hi> (as it is too <hi>irreligiously</hi> affirmed by many <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Patrons</hi> and <hi>Advocates</hi> for <hi>Perjury,</hi> in these perfidious Times) that these <hi>obligations</hi> by <hi>Oathes, Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Protestation,</hi> are all <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved, extinct,</hi> and <hi>void.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We shall onely examine what hath been asserted by <hi>Mr. John Dury</hi> to this purpose, who takes upon him in his <hi>Considerations, concerning the engagement,</hi> and <hi>his just</hi> Reproposals, to resolve the <hi>Conscience</hi> in this great Businesse; to which end he affirmes, <hi>That the oath of Allegiance is void,</hi> pag. 2. <hi>That the Covenant bindeth not▪</hi> pag. 7. <hi>That all Engagements in which we were bound to the King or Lords, are void,</hi> pag. 15. Reproposals.</p>
            <p>Now having seriously weighed his <hi>Arguments,</hi> by which he would <hi>confirme his Allegations,</hi> we shall consider <hi>distinctly</hi> of them, and shew their extreme <hi>unsatisfactorinesse</hi> to the <hi>Consciences</hi> of any, but such as through <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>interest</hi> desire to <hi>bribe, corrupt,</hi> and <hi>cozen</hi> their Consciences, that they may take it without <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the first place, concerning the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> to prove it <hi>void,</hi> he expasiates from page 2. to 4. upon this Supposition, which he maketh to be his onely <hi>Argument, That if the King be found unfaithfull in his trust, we are</hi> ipso facto <hi>absolved from our Allegiance unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:165546:14"/>
            <p>Now this being the marrow of this Proof, we shall shew the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satisfactorinesse</hi> of it to our judgement and consciences; and that not onely as 'tis laid down as a Supposition (with an <hi>If it can be made out</hi>) which he doth not in the least prove, but upon these Grounds following:</p>
            <p>First, if he had proved what he doth but suppose, <hi>That the King had been unfaithfull to his Trust,</hi> yet this <hi>dissolveth</hi> not the Oath of our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him.</p>
            <p>For first of all, the Oath is <hi>absolute,</hi> there is no such <hi>Condition</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in it, <hi>That if the King prove unlawfull to his Trust, that then our oath shall be void and null.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Allegiance to our Savereigne is our Duty,</hi> by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Land,</hi> though we were never <hi>engaged</hi> to it by Oath: otherwise such as were not <hi>obliged</hi> by the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> might for their <hi>Disloyalty to the King, be exempted</hi> from suffering as <hi>Traitors▪</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thirdly, the <hi>dissolving</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> from their Oathes upon neglect of <hi>Duty</hi> on the <hi>Magistrates</hi> part, is not onely <hi>contrary</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>expresse Texts of</hi> Scripture, that require <hi>obedience,</hi> not onely to <hi>good,</hi> but the <hi>froward, for Conscience sake.</hi> But <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Mr. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry's</hi> own judgement, who in his <hi>Considerations,</hi> pag. 11. is positive, <hi>That the Rule of</hi> Subjects <hi>behaviour, as</hi> Subjects, <hi>is clearly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in Rom. 13. 1. to 8. 1 Peter 2. 13, 14. &amp; Titus 3. 1. Where we finde nothing but a Command of</hi> Submission <hi>and</hi> Subjection <hi>of not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sting, and of paying Taxes and Dues, and of giving honour, fear, and respect for Conscience sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if this be the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> behaviour, as <hi>Subjects,</hi> that they are to be <hi>absolute</hi> in their <hi>obedience,</hi> without any <hi>limitation,</hi> further than (as he saith) <hi>that we are bound to obey God rather than Man, and to suffer patiently, where we finde cause to refuse obedience.</hi> Then Master <hi>John Dury</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>condemned by himselfe;</hi> and that which he <hi>supposeth</hi> to be the <hi>Ground</hi> of the <hi>dissolving</hi> the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> viz. <hi>a supposition of Abuse of Trust on the Kings part,</hi> is both <hi>false, absurd,</hi> and <hi>sinfull,</hi> by his own <hi>Argument;</hi> and therefore <hi>the Oath of Allegiance is not dissolved, but bindes the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science indispensably;</hi> notwithstanding all that Master <hi>Dury</hi> hath hath held forth to <hi>satisfie</hi> and <hi>resolve</hi> the <hi>Conscience.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:165546:14"/>
            <p>We now come in the next place, to examine his <hi>Grounds</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he builds the down-fall of the <hi>Covenant; For,</hi> saith he, <hi>page 7. Suppose that in your apprehensions this Engagement doth materially settle something in the Common-wealth, which is contrary to the Covenant; yet I say as matters now stand, you break not at all your Covenant, because your obligation to those matters by verture of your Covenant was extinguished: now that which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct and made void, cannot be said to oblige any more. And</hi> (saith he) <hi>all promises are</hi> ipso facto <hi>made void and extinct, in respect of the Tie upon the Conscience, when the thing promised is become in it selfe impossible to be done; or in reference to our Calling, unlawfull to be prosecuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Answer</hi> to his <hi>Grounds,</hi> though in the <hi>Thesi</hi> we grant, <hi>That then oathes, promises, and obligations do cease to binde, when they become impossible or unlawfull:</hi> yet we deny it to be so in the <hi>Hypothesi,</hi> in the <hi>present case</hi> of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> and therefore we shall examime and answer his <hi>Grounds</hi> particularly and <hi>distinctly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, saith he, <hi>It is impossible in Nature, to preserve the Kings life which is cut off, and the House of Lords which is already put down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>It is not lawfull for any in a private Calling, to attempt the restoring of that, which publike Power hath abolished.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in <hi>answer</hi> to the first, whereas he makes the <hi>Covenant</hi> to be <hi>impossible</hi> to be kept, <hi>the Kings life being cut off,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We conceive, that first according to the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England never dies;</hi> and that our <hi>obligation</hi> by the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> is not rendered <hi>impossible by the Death of King</hi> Charles <hi>the first,</hi> is evident, in that the <hi>Person</hi> of the <hi>King and his Authority,</hi> which are the <hi>objects</hi> of our <hi>Preservation,</hi> are supposed to be <hi>in being</hi> all the <hi>dayes of our lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, though it should be <hi>granted,</hi> that there is an <hi>impossibility</hi> in the matter of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> in relation to the <hi>Preservation</hi> of <hi>that Kings life</hi> then <hi>existent,</hi> yet <hi>Regal Authority,</hi> and the <hi>Kings Posterity,</hi> they are still in <hi>being,</hi> and it is unto <hi>them</hi> that we are <hi>obliged</hi> by our <hi>Solemne Covenant, and all those sacred Bonds that are upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:165546:15"/>
            <p>As for the <hi>impossibility</hi> of it in reference <hi>to the House of Lords</hi> which is already put down. We answer, that <hi>impossibility</hi> is onely <hi>present</hi> and not <hi>absolute,</hi> there is not a <hi>total cessation</hi> of all <hi>hopes of Recovery of our ancient Government by King and Lords,</hi> though at <hi>present</hi> it be <hi>violently obstructed,</hi> by such a Force as renders the keeping of our <hi>Covenant</hi> at present impossible. But being still <hi>in esse</hi> both <hi>King and House of Lords,</hi> we must take heed that we do not by the <hi>subscription</hi> of this <hi>Engagement, bury them alive,</hi> because in a weak and crazy condition, for this would not onely be <hi>Perjury,</hi> but great <hi>Injustice</hi> and <hi>cruelty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to his second <hi>Ground,</hi> that the <hi>Covenant</hi> is <hi>extinct</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> because <hi>unlawfull</hi> to be <hi>presented,</hi> it being <hi>not lawfull for any in a private calling to attempt the restoring of that which hath been abolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by publike Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We answer, that though it be <hi>unlawfull,</hi> for any in a <hi>private Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> or by a <hi>private Call,</hi> to attempt the <hi>restoring</hi> of that which hath been <hi>legally abolished by publike Authority,</hi> yet not to help to <hi>restore</hi> that which hath been <hi>suppressed</hi> or <hi>abolished by publike force</hi> and <hi>power of the sword,</hi> especially if they are <hi>obliged to preserve</hi> them in <hi>being</hi> (and consequently to restore them) <hi>against all force and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy, and to bring the Attempeers of it, if they be able, to condigne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment;</hi> which is our case.</p>
            <p>As to that which follows in the same Page, <hi>That if you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by promise to restore them, yet still it must be in, and according to our Callings, and as far as lawfully we may, not out of our Callings, or beyond them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We answer, It is true, and we desire to be <hi>conscientious</hi> in this particular. But by <hi>subscribing</hi> this <hi>Engagement,</hi> we disable our <hi>selves</hi> from our <hi>Duty</hi> in this respect, and so break our <hi>Covenant.</hi> For when we are <hi>called</hi> by a <hi>lawfull Power, with our lives, power, and estates, to performe our Promise, Vow, and Protestation, our Oathes, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> we are sinfully precluded by this <hi>Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be <hi>objected,</hi> that if the <hi>Covenant</hi> and other <hi>sacred</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Oathes of Allegiance</hi> are not <hi>extinct</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> upon the former Grounds; yet this present <hi>imposing</hi> Power hath made them <hi>null</hi> and <hi>void,</hi> by taking away all <hi>Allegiance from the Kings heires and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours,</hi> and by the institution of this <hi>new Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:165546:15"/>
            <p>To which we answer, that such a <hi>dispensation</hi> from them, would <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answer. </seg>
               </label> not onely be more then <hi>impious</hi> in them to <hi>propound,</hi> but exceeding <hi>ridiculous</hi> for us to believe. For how can we imagine a man that is <hi>manacled</hi> himself, to be able to <hi>unbinde</hi> and <hi>loose others.</hi> But now this is the Case of the present <hi>Imposers,</hi> that would <hi>absolve us;</hi> themselves being <hi>obliged</hi> by all those <hi>Sacred Bonds</hi> (and that with so fast a <hi>knot,</hi> that in one Oath which they have assuredly taken, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Oath of Supremacy</hi>) they do <hi>professe;</hi> that <hi>they do beleeve, and are in conscience perswaded, that neither the Pope, or any other person whatsoever, hath power to absolve them of this Oath, or any part thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that <hi>de facto</hi> they are <hi>excluded</hi> from being able to dis-oblige us from those sacred chains. Now that they are excluded <hi>de jure</hi> also, is very evident. <hi>Jure divino,</hi> according to the judgement of all Divines, grounded upon the Scriptures; <hi>It is not in the power of any creature, to absolve us from an Oath lawfull and possible to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</hi> And <hi>Jure humane,</hi> they are likewise excluded from any such power; for in the <hi>statute</hi> of the 13. of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it is expresly conferred upon the <hi>three Estates in Parliament,</hi> the <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> to alter the <hi>Fundamentall Lawes and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Land, by Oath established:</hi> but not upon the <hi>Commons,</hi> though <hi>Free</hi> and <hi>Full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that we may the more <hi>convinceingly</hi> demonstrate, that all those <hi>Sacred Oathes</hi> [the <hi>Protestation,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi>] are still binding to our <hi>Consciences;</hi> (besides what hath been already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) we shall adde some further Considerations, from the words that are in those sacred Ties. Omitting therefore what wee last mentioned, concerning <hi>that passage in the Oath of Supremacy;</hi> wee finde, that the <hi>Covenant</hi> was not <hi>pro tempore,</hi> binding onely during the present <hi>Exigent</hi> we were then in, <hi>But that we are obliged to keep every Article thereof, constantly and zealously, all the dayes of our lives:</hi> so that nothing but <hi>death,</hi> which dissolveth the knot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween our <hi>Bodies</hi> and our <hi>Souls,</hi> can <hi>dissolve</hi> this <hi>Covenant,</hi> and set us at liberty to be free for other engagements. And that the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 5. 1649. hath still the same obligation upon us, and none <hi>but God</hi> onely can <hi>absolve</hi> us from it; <hi>appeareth,</hi> in that we have not onely <hi>protested,</hi> but have <hi>promised</hi> and <hi>vowed</hi> in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165546:16"/>
               <hi>presence of Almighty God,</hi> that with our <hi>lives, power,</hi> and <hi>estates,</hi> we will maintain and defend, not the <hi>Kings person</hi> onely, but <hi>His Honour and Estate,</hi> as also the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower and Priviledges of Parliament,</hi> the lawfull <hi>Rights and Liberties of the Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that we will <hi>oppose</hi> such as shall by <hi>force</hi> or <hi>conspiracy</hi> do any thing to the <hi>contrary,</hi> and that we will neither <hi>for hope, fear, or other respect, relinquish this Promise, Vow, or Protestation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which <hi>Passages,</hi> with many other in the said <hi>obligations,</hi> it is most <hi>evident</hi> that all those <hi>sacred oathes</hi> are still <hi>binding;</hi> and that therefore <hi>to subscribe the Engagement,</hi> which hath been <hi>proved</hi> is so <hi>point blanke</hi> against them, must needs be <hi>sinfull</hi> and <hi>unlawfull,</hi> upon this account, in respect of the <hi>quis,</hi> relating not onely to the <hi>Prescribers,</hi> but also to the <hi>Subscribers,</hi> who being (as hath been <hi>proved</hi>) so <hi>indispensably engaged,</hi> cannot <hi>subscribe</hi> to this, without <hi>perspicuous Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus having now examined <hi>this present Engagement, to be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth, as it is now established with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King and House of Lords;</hi> by two of those <hi>Circumstances,</hi> which render <hi>Engagements to be sinfull,</hi> the <hi>quis</hi> and the <hi>quid</hi> of it, omitting the <hi>consideration</hi> of the <hi>quibus</hi> or the <hi>cui,</hi> the Persons with whom, and to whom we do <hi>engage</hi> our selves, because <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident</hi> with what we have said in relation to the <hi>quis,</hi> as referring to the Power <hi>imposing this Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We shall now come <hi>to consider</hi> of another <hi>Circumstance,</hi> that renders <hi>Engagements</hi> in the <hi>general</hi> to be <hi>sinfull;</hi> and that is the <hi>cur,</hi> or the <hi>quare;</hi> the <hi>end</hi> wherefore we enter into <hi>Engagements.</hi> Now if the <hi>end</hi> appear to be <hi>sinfull,</hi> so also will be the <hi>Engagement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that the <hi>end</hi> of this <hi>Engagement</hi> is <hi>sinfull,</hi> is very <hi>obvious</hi> to the dimmest sight: for though it be <hi>expressed</hi> in the said <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in terminis,</hi> yet the <hi>Eradication</hi> of <hi>Monarchy</hi> (under which this <hi>Nation</hi> hath flourished for so many <hi>Generations,</hi> and which we are engaged <hi>to maintain, and preserve</hi> by so many <hi>obligations</hi>) and also <hi>the settlement of a prodigious Polarchy,</hi> whose <hi>Foundation</hi> hath been laid in <hi>Rebellion, Murder, Treachery,</hi> and <hi>Perjury,</hi> are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed <hi>ends</hi> of this <hi>Engagement;</hi> and not onely so, but <hi>to deprive the the lawfull Heir unto the Crown of his Birth-right,</hi> which is <hi>to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> in the <hi>Throne,</hi> not onely <hi>by the Laws of the Land,</hi> in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165546:16"/> by the <hi>statute</hi> of the <hi>first of King Iames, Chap.</hi> 1. 2. wherein the <hi>whole kingdome</hi> do engage themselves to <hi>King Iames, his Heirs, Successours, and posteritie for ever;</hi> To <hi>defend their undoubted right to the Crown, with the last drop of their bloud:</hi> But also, by all those <hi>Sacred Oathes of Supremacie, Allegiance, and of a Free-man, &amp;c.</hi> which to do is sinfull and unjust.</p>
            <p>But to this it is implyed by Mr. <hi>Dury,</hi> pag. 18, 19. That to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the lawfull Heir of the Crown from his Right,</hi> and to alter the Constitution of the Parliament, by nulling the House of Lords, <hi>is but a seeming inconveniency;</hi> but to subscribe the <hi>Engagement,</hi> is an <hi>indispensable duty. The one, is but the seeming Violation of the particular Right of some few persons, which is or may be doubtfull whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you are engaged thereunto or no. But to engage, is a duty which relates to the whole Cemmonwealth, the safety of all, and our own necessary peace and preservation.</hi> And Pag. 20. (saith he) <hi>as for the dissolution of your Tye to the Heir of the Crown, I shall refer you to look upon God, whether he hath not dispossessed him wholly by his own doings, and confesse, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for Answer unto these <hi>groundlesse Assertions,</hi> and <hi>confused Suppositions</hi> of his, under which he doth <hi>extenuate</hi> most <hi>crying provocations;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We shall propose and prove these three Assertions: First, that to exclude the <hi>Right Heir</hi> of the Crown, which is the <hi>end</hi> of this <hi>Engagement,</hi> is not only a <hi>seeming inconveniency,</hi> but a <hi>complicated wickednesse,</hi> made up of <hi>Injustice, Disloyalty,</hi> and <hi>Treachery.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that to subscribe the Engagement, is no <hi>indispensable duty</hi> that relates to the good of the whole Commonwealth. And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the present forcible extrusion and dispossession of the right Heir of the Crown, cannot without horrid impiety, be charged upon God, the righteous Judge of the whole world.</p>
            <p>But having (wee hope) sufficiently proved the two former already, wee shall to his third <hi>Supposition</hi> (Pag. 20.) <hi>That w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are dissolved from our Tye to the Heir of the Crown, and that it is done by God, whom he saith, hath done what is good in his own eyes,</hi> &amp;c. with abundance of such <hi>Independent Conclusions,</hi> upon which, hee with his <hi>Posted BRETHREN</hi> have (as hee professeth for them all) taken this <hi>Engagement</hi> as a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165546:17"/> duty, <hi>Just Proposals, Pag. 10. Because God hath altered by an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary way the Government,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We reply, that as we have already proved that <hi>Tie</hi> and <hi>obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> that is upon us, to the <hi>right Heir to the Crown,</hi> to be still <hi>binding,</hi> notwithstanding his forcible <hi>expulsion.</hi> So, to say, that God hath <hi>wholly dispossest</hi> him, because that <hi>at this time</hi> there are others in the <hi>actual Possession of the ruling Power,</hi> which Master <hi>Dury</hi> implies, <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. of his <hi>Considerations.</hi> We conceive, cannot be charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>just</hi> and <hi>righteous</hi> God, in whom <hi>there is no iniquity,</hi> without making him <hi>the Authour,</hi> if not <hi>Approver</hi> of such unheard of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury</hi> and <hi>Injustice,</hi> which <hi>to thinke</hi> were <hi>Blasphemy.</hi> We grant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, this <hi>great Change</hi> now in the <hi>Kingdom, effected</hi> by those <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> and <hi>extrajudicial</hi> Acts of <hi>Murder, Treachery,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,</hi> is not come about without <hi>the determinate Counsel of God,</hi> by which <hi>Judas</hi> brought our <hi>Saviour</hi> to his <hi>Crosse;</hi> and that <hi>Permis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Providence</hi> by which <hi>Absalom</hi> and <hi>Adonijah</hi> for a <hi>time</hi> usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Kingdom of <hi>Israel.</hi> But that the wise and holy <hi>Providence</hi> of God permitting this, should be interpreted <hi>Gods disposing</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> or <hi>Solomon;</hi> and that God is doing that which is good in his own eyes, and should be a ground for <hi>the Subjects Engagements</hi> to them, with the <hi>violation</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> of God upon them, cannot be <hi>maintained</hi> without <hi>dishonour to God himselfe,</hi> great <hi>injustice</hi> to the <hi>lawfull Magistrate,</hi> and plunging our <hi>souls</hi> into the Pit of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, <hi>the end of this Engagement</hi> being <hi>to exclude the right Heir of the Crown, to extirpate and subvert kingly Government,</hi> and <hi>to introduce</hi> through much <hi>complicated iniquity,</hi> a <hi>monstrous</hi> and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-headed Government,</hi> which must be <hi>supported</hi> by most <hi>horrid op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions</hi> and <hi>heavy Taxations,</hi> under which (the original of all just Power) the People must crouch, with such silent submission, as for to say publikely, <hi>that it is Tyrannical,</hi> shall cost them their <hi>lives,</hi> and all <hi>that is dear</hi> unto them.</p>
            <p>It appeareth, that though <hi>to engage to be true and faithfull</hi> be a <hi>duty,</hi> and not <hi>simply sinfull</hi> in it selfe, yet in respect of the <hi>matter</hi> of it, <hi>relating</hi> to the <hi>object of the Engagement, The Common-wealth of England,</hi> as to a <hi>Government;</hi> and <hi>the qualification of the object, as it is now established without a King and House of Lords, circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:165546:17"/> with the <hi>quis, relating to the Prescribers,</hi> whom we have <hi>proved</hi> have no <hi>lawfull Power</hi> over others, and to the <hi>Subscribers,</hi> which have no Power over themselves; and likewise with the <hi>cur, realting to the end of subscribing</hi> the whole <hi>Engagement, to be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth of England,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is unlawfull, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient,</hi> and therefore <hi>sinfull,</hi> in the highest degree. And conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>to subscribe it,</hi> if there were no more in it than what M. <hi>Dury</hi> in his <hi>Reproposals</hi> doth affirme is declared thereby;</p>
            <p>First, <hi>our approbation of the present Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>our ratifying consent unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thirdly, <hi>our obligation towards the present establishment,</hi> doth render it to be out of measure <hi>sinfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, passing over many other frivolous and groundlesse <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations</hi> of Master <hi>Dury's,</hi> in his <hi>Considerations</hi> and <hi>Reproposals,</hi> for <hi>to subscribe the Engagment;</hi> as flowing from such <hi>Principles,</hi> which he takes for <hi>granted</hi> himselfe, and therefore <hi>magisterially</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds them in his own <hi>name,</hi> without <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reason.</hi> As that <hi>the Imposers are our Rulers and Governours. Reproposals. pag.</hi> 8. And <hi>to subscribe the Engagement, is a duty just, to be required by the present Powers from their Subjects, Consider. pag.</hi> 16. And <hi>that to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe it</hi> is a <hi>duty, Repropos. pag. 7. A clear and confessed duty, Pa. 12. A lawfull and necessary duty, Pag.</hi> 13. All which we have fully dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
            <p>We shall onely <hi>answer</hi> two or three <hi>Allegations</hi> more, which are urged by some for our <hi>subscription,</hi> and so conclude.</p>
            <p>In the first place, we have heard it alledged by some, <hi>that to scruple the Engagement,</hi> because <hi>pre-engaged</hi> by former <hi>Oathes to the King, his heires, and successours,</hi> is altogether <hi>a needlesse scruple:</hi> because <hi>oathes</hi> for <hi>fealty</hi> and <hi>allegiance</hi> were <hi>enforced</hi> upon our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestours</hi> by <hi>William the Conquerour,</hi> being therefore but the <hi>Badges of that Norman Yoak that was put upon us.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> being now dead, and his <hi>Posterity dis-inherited,</hi> we are now free from our <hi>obligations,</hi> in these Times of the <hi>Peoples Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for <hi>answer</hi> to this, though it should be <hi>granted,</hi> that such <hi>oathes</hi> should <hi>originally</hi> be <hi>enforced</hi> upon our <hi>Ancestours</hi> by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour,</hi> (which we have <hi>intimated</hi> to the <hi>contrary</hi> from the Lord <hi>Keepers</hi> Speech in <hi>Parliament</hi>) yet in severall <hi>Ages</hi> the <hi>sacred Ties</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:165546:18"/> have been confirmed by a <hi>Parliamentary Power,</hi> to be imposed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole <hi>Kingdom,</hi> especially in relation to our <hi>late King, his heirs, successours, and Posterity</hi> for ever, as appeareth in that <hi>Act 1. Jacob. c.</hi> 1, 2. But were not this our condition, but that through <hi>force,</hi> and as a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eople conquered,</hi> we had <hi>engaged</hi> our selves by <hi>Oath, To be true and faithfull,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>forcible Imposition</hi> doth no way take off the <hi>force of the Obligation.</hi> Though <hi>Zedekiah</hi> were by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest</hi> brought into <hi>subjection</hi> unto <hi>Nebuchodonozer,</hi> yet this being <hi>confirmed by an Oath</hi> to the said <hi>King, his violation of it</hi> is accounted a <hi>despising of the Oath of God,</hi> which he doth <hi>threaten to bring upon his head, Ezech 17. v. 19. Thus saith the Lord, as I live, I will surely bring my Oath that he hath despised, and my Covenant that he hath broken upon his own head, vers. 20. And I will enter into judgement with him for his trespasse that he hath committed against me.</hi> So that, <hi>to break an oath of subjectien to a Conquerour, is a Trespasse against God himselfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is further alledged, <hi>we may lawfully subscribe this</hi> Engagement <hi>though the</hi> imposing Powers <hi>are such as have by the Sword got the</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>into their hands. If we were a</hi> conquered People, <hi>either by the</hi> Turke, <hi>the</hi> Pope, <hi>or the</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Spain, <hi>we are to be in subjection to them, as</hi> Conquerours, <hi>their Conquest giving them a Title to</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>To this we <hi>answer,</hi> that it hath not yet been <hi>alleadged</hi> by the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers of this Engagement, that we are a conquered People,</hi> though we must needs say, <hi>that we are a cozened People; through the abuse of the trust which was put into the hands of the</hi> Imposers, <hi>both in</hi> Councel <hi>and</hi> Campe, for which we are absolved from any <hi>fealty</hi> and <hi>allegiance</hi> to them, if any had been by Master <hi>Dury's</hi> judgement in the Case of the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, were it our condition, <hi>that we are conquered and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued,</hi> yet then <hi>were we to submit</hi> unto such a <hi>Power</hi> onely in <hi>lawfull things,</hi> and <hi>things necessary</hi> for the <hi>preservation</hi> of our selves and others; but <hi>to subscribe this Engagement,</hi> appeareth to be altogether <hi>unlawfull,</hi> and no way necessary to the <hi>preservation</hi> of our selves or others, unlesse it be <hi>to keep</hi> and <hi>preserve</hi> us in our <hi>enslaved</hi> and <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is alleadged, <hi>that though the</hi> government <hi>of the</hi> Kingdme
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165546:18"/>
               <hi>was altered in an</hi> extraordinary <hi>and</hi> extrajudicial <hi>way, yet God having blessed it with such</hi> extraordinary Successes <hi>both in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>by which he hath sealed his approbation of it, why should not you come in, and seal your approbation of it also, by your subsciption to this Engagement, To be true and faithfull?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this we <hi>answer,</hi> that <hi>successe in sinfull wayes,</hi> as it must be no <hi>ground</hi> for our <hi>compliance</hi> or <hi>approbation,</hi> who do professe our <hi>Guide</hi> to be <hi>the Law and the Testimonies.</hi> So neither can it be <hi>a Seal of Gods approbation.</hi> For though we finde that <hi>usurpation</hi> was attended with <hi>successe,</hi> as it was for <hi>three years</hi> together in <hi>Bramble Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech's</hi> time, <hi>Judges 6. v.</hi> 22. yet after the <hi>successe</hi> in the ruining the men of <hi>Shechem,</hi> his own Party, which were instrumental in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to the <hi>government,</hi> and in taking in many strong Holds and Garrisons, <hi>putting them to the sword, vers.</hi> 45, 49, 50. The <hi>Lord</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>dis-approbation,</hi> by a suddain and ignominious Death, as we reade <hi>vers.</hi> 53. 54.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Abimelech</hi> found in conclusion after three years <hi>successe</hi> that God approved not of his <hi>usurping the Goverument,</hi> but execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his vengeance by a miserable Death.</p>
            <p>So we finde, that <hi>Absalom,</hi> who although in the Language of <hi>the Northerne subscribers Plea for the Engagement,</hi> pag. 10. might look upon his <hi>succesfull flattery, hypocrisie, rebellion,</hi> and <hi>usurping the Government of Israel,</hi> as a <hi>wonderfull appearing</hi> for him, yet in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion he came to confusion; and the Lord appeared to be so farre from owning or approving his <hi>usurped Power,</hi> nowithstanding <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer successes,</hi> that he was by <hi>Providence</hi> brought to such an end, he might affright any from presuming to be his Successours in <hi>disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, treachery,</hi> and <hi>usurpation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be objected, <hi>that surely you are more baptized into the spirit of Atheisme than the</hi> Egyptian <hi>Sorcerers that withstood</hi> Moses, <hi>or else you would never produce such an infamous instance as that of</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salom, <hi>to parallel with these</hi> present Powers, <hi>whom God hath so</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved <hi>of, as he hath done. He will surely curse that man and his house, that saith, it was an arme of flesh that did what was done in</hi> England, <hi>as making way for this Change, or what hath been done in</hi> Ireland <hi>since▪ North. Plea,</hi> pag. 10. where he refers to Master <hi>Cromwels</hi> Letter from <hi>Ireland, Decemb.</hi> 1649. to this purpose.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:165546:19"/>
            <p>Now in <hi>answer to this objection,</hi> because that we finde the <hi>North subscribers</hi> in the <hi>Plea</hi> for the <hi>Engagement,</hi> laying down this <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> for their <hi>subscription,</hi> viz. <hi>The being of these present Powers over us from God, Pag.</hi> 7. Testified by <hi>those extraordinary successes, Pag.</hi> 9, 10. where they say, <hi>This is the main foundation upon which they build their obedience, being of such powerfull and direct influences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Consciences, Pag.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>We shall enlarge upon our <hi>Parallel,</hi> between <hi>Absalom</hi> and the <hi>Ʋtopian Powers,</hi> and shew what a sandy <hi>foundation Prosperity</hi> and <hi>Successe,</hi> is for <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>Allegiance to usurped Powers;</hi> and that it doth not in the least, seal <hi>Gods approbation</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>And because, our <hi>North subscribers</hi> lay claim <hi>to Gods signal</hi> evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencing of his <hi>approving the present Change of Government, by those wonderfull Appearings of God, antecedent, concomitant,</hi> and <hi>subsequent</hi> to the same, <hi>Pag. 10. lin.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>We shall first consider the <hi>Antecedent Appearances of Providence</hi> succeeding <hi>Absalom,</hi> before that he discovered his <hi>ambitious</hi> and <hi>treacherous Designe of usurping the Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the first place, knowing that if he could but be <hi>Master</hi> of the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> of the <hi>Kings Subjects,</hi> he would soon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand both their <hi>heads, hands,</hi> and <hi>purses.</hi> He so farre succeeded in his <hi>Machiviliau</hi> be-spattering of the <hi>Kings Government, 2 Sam. 15. 3. Insinuating,</hi> that the <hi>King</hi> was altogether <hi>carelesse of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jests welfare.</hi> And therefore <hi>there was none deputed to hear the Cause, though never so just and righteous, vers.</hi> 3. And in his subtle <hi>intimations</hi> of his deep sense of <hi>the Peoples sufferings,</hi> attended with a <hi>Profession</hi> of his readinesse <hi>to relieve them, and do them justice, if he were but once made a Judge in the Land, vers.</hi> 4. That it is said, <hi>he did steal away the hearts of the People of Israel.</hi> So that it is <hi>evident,</hi> that by the <hi>antecedent Appearances of Providence,</hi> his <hi>Designe</hi> was very <hi>succesfull,</hi> and he might say with those <hi>oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours, Zach. 11. 5. Blessed be the Lord, for I am rich;</hi> I am like to get the <hi>Crown,</hi> my <hi>Designe</hi> takes according to my <hi>hearts desire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now in the next place, lest <hi>Absalom</hi> should fall short of his <hi>expectation,</hi> for want of an <hi>oportunity</hi> to get the <hi>Militia</hi> into his hands, and the <hi>People</hi> (whose <hi>hearts he had stollen away) into a Body.</hi> We shall finde in the Language of the <hi>North subscribers, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165546:19"/> smoothing that roughnesse,</hi> and making him so <hi>succesfull,</hi> as that the <hi>King</hi> himselfe doth become <hi>instrumental</hi> in that very worke; for having <hi>varnished,</hi> and guilded over his <hi>Designe</hi> with a religious <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>keeping his Vow and Covenant,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> not onely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misseth him, but sends him away with a <hi>blessing</hi> to <hi>Hebron, 2 Sam.</hi> 15. 7. By which meanes he had an <hi>oportunity</hi> to get the People about him; and whilest he was at his <hi>pretended devotion, to increase the Commotion,</hi> for it is said, <hi>vers. 12. Whilest he offered sacrifices, the People increased still with Absalom.</hi> Having thus <hi>succeeded</hi> in laying of this <hi>Designe,</hi> we shall consider of the <hi>concomitant and succeeding Providences</hi> with which this <hi>wicked wretch</hi> might have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed as well as the <hi>Ʋtopian</hi> Powers.</p>
            <p>As first, his <hi>forcing</hi> and <hi>driving</hi> away the <hi>King</hi> from his <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> the Imperial City <hi>Jerusalem, 2 Sam</hi> 15. 14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his <hi>glorious entrance into the same himselfe,</hi> taking pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of the <hi>Palace Royal, 2 Sam.</hi> 15. 16. And being there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for the <hi>supreme Magistrate, vers.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his being <hi>possessed</hi> of all the <hi>Land</hi> unto <hi>Jordan,</hi> whilest the <hi>King</hi> was forced <hi>to retreat to Mahanaim by the Fourd Jabbok, 2 Sam.</hi> 17. 24. Now here was an <hi>un-interrupted series</hi> of <hi>good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse,</hi> for a great while together; enough to induce many to do that really, which <hi>Hushai</hi> did <hi>politiquely, 2 Sam. 16. 17. Acknowledge</hi> this <hi>Monster</hi> of <hi>Mankinde,</hi> to be <hi>chosen</hi> to the <hi>Government</hi> by the <hi>Lord himselfe, and all the men of Israel.</hi> And to say with <hi>Shimeah, 1 Kings</hi> 12. 24. Returne <hi>every man to his house, for this thing is from the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet notwithstanding, the <hi>Lord</hi> to vindicate his own glory, by making <hi>known</hi> to the World, how much he hateth such horrid <hi>hypocrisie, treachery,</hi> and <hi>usurpation,</hi> not onely put a period to his prosperity, by punishing that <hi>unnatural</hi> and <hi>rebellious Ʋsurper</hi> with an ignominious death, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 9. but also shewed his direfull displeasure against those that <hi>engaged</hi> with him, <hi>vers.</hi> 7. there being <hi>twenty thousand of his Confederates slain also the same day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which it <hi>appeares,</hi> that the <hi>successe</hi> of an <hi>usurping Power,</hi> though to the present <hi>dis-possession</hi> of the <hi>lawfull Magistrate,</hi> is no <hi>evidence of Gods approbation</hi> of it, nor can be a <hi>Scripture-ground</hi> for <hi>obedience</hi> or <hi>all egiance</hi> to it.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:165546:20"/>
            <p>And that therefore, as we cannot in <hi>Conscience</hi> be perswaded of the <hi>lawfulnesse of subscribing this Engagement,</hi> upon such a <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan Principle;</hi> so we must needs rejoyce in the <hi>faithfulnesse</hi> of all those <hi>lerned, orthodox,</hi> and <hi>consciencious Ministers</hi> amongst us, who though they are much <hi>condemned</hi> by many in these <hi>sinfull Times,</hi> for their <hi>non-compliance</hi> with <hi>Absalonisme,</hi> yet are they <hi>justified</hi> by <hi>Radok, Abiathar,</hi> and those <hi>godly Levites,</hi> that would not worship <hi>the rising Sun,</hi> nor forgo their <hi>Allegiance to their oppressed Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne, 2 Sam.</hi> 15. 24, 29.</p>
            <p>But it may be further objected, <hi>How can ye, who have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes well affected to the</hi> common Cause of Liberty, <hi>against the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe of</hi> Tyranny; <hi>and that have acted so highly against the Forces raised by the late King? How can ye refuse the subscribing this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, withoui deserting the godly and faithfull in the Land, and adhering to the</hi> Malignant <hi>Party, which ye have opposed all this while?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which we <hi>answer,</hi> that in <hi>declining</hi> and <hi>opposing this Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> we do not <hi>apostatize</hi> in the least from our first <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>opposition of Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>contending for the lawfull Rights,</hi> and <hi>the Liberties of the Kingdom;</hi> but our <hi>opposing</hi> and <hi>refusing this Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as a <hi>sinfull support</hi> unto <hi>usurpation</hi> is a clear <hi>evidence</hi> of the uprightnesse of our aimes and ends, in what we did at first upon <hi>the Parliaments Remonstrance.</hi> For if we should now <hi>close</hi> with <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>usurpation</hi> (because now carried on by some Persons whom we otherwise honour and love for their <hi>Profession of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi>) we should <hi>demonstrate</hi> our <hi>opposition of tyranny and oppression</hi> out of <hi>faction;</hi> not because the thing was evil in it selfe, but as it was an evil in such Persons that we did not reverence and esteem.</p>
            <p>As for an appearance of <hi>adhering to Malignants,</hi> which we have all this while opposed. We <hi>answer,</hi> that this refusing of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,</hi> is no such <hi>Indication;</hi> for we desire nothing more than to be in a capacity according to our <hi>Covenant, of bringing all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, and evil Instruments that have hindered the Reformation of Religion, divided the King from his People, and one Kingdom from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and made a faction amongst the People</hi> to condigne Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But it may be also objected, Can ye deny but that this <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:165546:20"/> is, and hath <hi>subscribed</hi> by many that are <hi>truly godly.</hi> Why then should ye by this your <hi>opposition</hi> and <hi>scrupelosity</hi> make your selves more <hi>wise, holy,</hi> and <hi>conscientious</hi> than they?</p>
            <p>For <hi>answer</hi> to this, though we grant it, that it is <hi>possible,</hi> that there are many <hi>godly Persons</hi> whose understandings being <hi>muffled,</hi> by Master <hi>Dury's Sophistry,</hi> may in <hi>the simplicity of their hearts sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe this Engagement,</hi> as <hi>the People followed Absalom in his Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Yet comparing them with the number of those that do it upon Designe, as for <hi>to keep up that ungodly Toleration that is yet permitted to errour and heresie: to keep themselves still in Places▪ of Profit and Advantage, out of which others are excluded; or to preserve themselves from being called to account for all those extrajudicial Proceedings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We think we may <hi>without breach of Charity,</hi> conclude their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to be very few; but yet if they were many more than they are, and such as were of good repute for <hi>godlinesse,</hi> yet we are to be followers of their example no further than we finde them to be <hi>followers of Christ, and of his will revealed in his Word;</hi> neither must we set the <hi>Watch</hi> of our <hi>Consciences</hi> by the <hi>Consciences</hi> of others, but by the <hi>Sun-diall</hi> of the sacred <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now for our <hi>vindication</hi> of what we have done in <hi>disputing the Right and Title of the present Imposers of this Engagement,</hi> and discovering <hi>the unlawfulnesse</hi> and <hi>inexpediency of it.</hi> We shall <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude</hi> with a short <hi>answer</hi> to what is alleadged by Master <hi>Dury</hi> against this practice of ours, who in his <hi>Reproposals, pag.</hi> 11. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth <hi>Reasons, why none should question the Imposers of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, nor interpret it as the Proposers have done. It is</hi> (saith he) <hi>not onely preposterous, and contrary to the nature of healing of Breaches, and of advancing of publike good in this time of distraction, but incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with charity, and opposite to that wisdom which is from above, teaching us to have pure and peaceable thoughts in all our actings, to performe Duties in godly simplicity, and without worldly wisdom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To all which we shall onely say, That if Master <hi>Dury</hi> can <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe</hi> no better way <hi>to heal our Breach,</hi> than by <hi>the use of such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered morter;</hi> no way <hi>to advance the publike good</hi> in this time of distraction, but <hi>by subscribing this sinfull Engagement</hi> without the least dispute or contradiction. As we cannot much wonder that the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165546:21"/> pains he hath taken in <hi>healing the Breaches between the Calvinists and Lutherans</hi> hath been to so little purpose. So we must needs say, that this <hi>Argument</hi> for <hi>blinde obedience to this Act for subscription without any dispute or examination of the lawfulnesse of it.</hi> (Because it would demonstrate <hi>our godly simplicity, gentlenesse, and easinesse to be entreated.</hi>) is not onely <hi>contrary</hi> unto Master <hi>John Goodwin's</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Antecavelerisme</hi> from <hi>pag. 18. to</hi> 22, where he hath six <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> for his <hi>Confutation</hi> and our <hi>Vindication:</hi> but is an <hi>exceeding simple</hi> and <hi>sinfull Argument;</hi> and that because it not onely <hi>condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Generation of the just</hi> in former Times, who have <hi>with the three Children disputed, questioned,</hi> and <hi>opposed unlawfull Commands with undaunted resolution:</hi> but also <hi>condemneth</hi> all that hath been done <hi>by this Generation, in their refusing Conformity to superstitious Innovations</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>illegal Impositions in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> as being <hi>contrary to the nature of healing of Breaches, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with the wisdom that is from above:</hi> and as testifying their <hi>godly simplicity,</hi> and that they have not been such who should have been <hi>gentle and easie to be entreated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we adde further, that had this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Master <hi>Dury's</hi> for <hi>blinde obedience,</hi> and <hi>non-resistance of the present Powers</hi> from <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and other places, being preached at the <hi>beginning</hi> of these <hi>Troubles</hi> by Master <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> Master <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> and many other of <hi>the present State Chaplains.</hi> In stead of <hi>conjuring</hi> us to stand up for our <hi>Liberties,</hi> and not to be afraid, but <hi>to fight</hi> for our <hi>Brethren, our Sons, and Daughters, our Wives and our houses, Nehem.</hi> 4. 14. Which was Master <hi>Peters</hi> frequent <hi>Text,</hi> when he preached away our <hi>Plate</hi> and <hi>Apprentices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>King</hi> had not onely been upon his <hi>Throne,</hi> and our <hi>money</hi> in our <hi>Purses,</hi> but our <hi>fields</hi> had never been <hi>dunged</hi> with the dead Carcases of so many thousand of our slaughtered <hi>Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though all this be come upon us, through <hi>the cunning crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> of some, whom we now see had an <hi>ungodly Designe for the Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of Monarchy, the King, and his Posterity,</hi> when <hi>they with the Parliament</hi> awakened us, <hi>to the defence of our Liberties▪</hi> and not to lie crouching down with <hi>Issachar,</hi> between our <hi>Burthens; which being effected,</hi> they would now have supported <hi>by subscribing this</hi> sinfull <hi>Engagement,</hi> without dispute, as the way <hi>to heal our Breaches and to testifie our godly simplicity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:165546:21"/>
            <p>Yet shall not we fall from our <hi>first Principles, deal unfaithfully with our Covenant, or let go our integrity till we die.</hi> But as our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences do witnesse that we had no such Designes</hi> in our chearfull and cordial assistance <hi>of the Parliament with our Lives and Fortunes, To preserve the true Protestant Religion, the Kings Majesties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament, and the Liberty of the Subject▪</hi> So <hi>to witnesse to the world our souls abhorrency of what hath been done unto the contrary, and that we cannot in Conscience consent unto it,</hi> or <hi>ratifie</hi> the same by our <hi>Subscription</hi> to this sinfull <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which would make us <hi>medlers with those that are given to change, Prov.</hi> 24. 21. We say with <hi>Pilate</hi> in another Case, <hi>What we have written, we have written.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>